<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Nate Speller]]></title>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-14T22:40:39-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://yoursite.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nathan Speller]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sticking to Your Goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/blog/2012/10/14/internal-dialogue/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-14T22:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/blog/2012/10/14/internal-dialogue</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a given day, who do you talk to most? A co-worker? Best friend? A significant other?</p>

<p>I&#8217;m willing to bet that there&#8217;s another person you speak to more. One that never stops talking to you, and never waits for your response. One that criticizes all your actions, second-guesses all your decisions, and nags you endlessly about how little you&#8217;ve accomplished. No, it&#8217;s not your mother and it&#8217;s not your ex.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s you.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s that voice in your head that never seems to quit:</p>

<blockquote>&#8220;I&#8217;ll start that personal project tomorrow&#8221;<br>
&#8220;geez, everyone else is so much more successful&#8221;</blockquote>


<blockquote>&#8220;just one more article and then I&#8217;ll start my work&#8221;<br>
&#8220;ugh, I&#8217;m so lazy&#8221;</blockquote>


<blockquote>&#8220;just one more slice of pie&#8221;<br>
  &#8220;OMG I&#8217;m so fat&#8221;</blockquote>


<p>You&#8217;ve tried to fix the situation with motivational youtube videos, new workout buddies, the latest to-do lists (to-do lists for your to-do lists), etc. You get excited about your new found motivation. You get pumped: &#8220;I got this!!! There&#8217;s no way I can fail this time!!&#8221;</p>

<p>Yet the internal dialogue brings you down eventually.</p>

<p>Now don&#8217;t blame the to-do list for your failure. The problem is not about staying in your heightened state of motivation. It&#8217;s about perservering when all you want to do is flop on the couch with a sheet cake and watch New Girl. But how? The first step to overcoming this is separating yourself from your internal dialogue.</p>

<h2>Listen to your tone</h2>


<p>Often you&#8217;ll get so lost in your internal dialogue that you won&#8217;t realize the stress you&#8217;re causing yourself.</p>

<blockquote>&#8220;Ugh, I&#8217;m so lazy. I gotta start exercising. Where did these rolls come from?? I can&#8217;t go out with a gut like this. Oh they&#8217;re looking at me now. They&#8217;re probably thinking &#8216;Wow, look at that guy, I can&#8217;t believe he&#8217;s drinking during his third trimester&#8217;&#8221;</blockquote>


<p>In these cases, the actual words of your internal dialogue don&#8217;t matter. What matters is the tone. Stop and take out the words, using only &#8220;mmm&#8221; sounds and you&#8217;ll quickly discover the mood you&#8217;re in. Sounding whiny? Kill that internal dialogue on spot, make a decision, and stop worrying.</p>

<h2>Listen to your phrasing</h2>


<p>Now lets put the words back in and take a look at your phrasing. This is an often talked about topic for new parents. When a child misbehaves, it&#8217;s said that you should denounce the action, yet praise the child. i.e. &#8220;she is a good kid who has done something wrong&#8221; - rather than &#8220;she is a terrible kid&#8221;.</p>

<p>Now how does this relate to internal dialogue? Many people will do the opposite in their internal dialogue: &#8220;Im a lazy, unmotivated person. But today I went to the gym - I did good today&#8221;. Here, this person defines himself by the negative attributes and unintentionally creates a tremendous mental hurdle. Rather one should think &#8220;I went to the gym today because I&#8217;m disciplined and dedicated to achieving my goal.&#8221;</p>

<p>You hear this kind of advice from others all the time:</p>

<blockquote>&#8220;There are those who think they will succeed and those who think they will fail. In the end, both are right.&#8221;</blockquote>


<blockquote>&#8220;Believe in yourself.&#8221;</blockquote>


<p></p>

<p>The subtlety to this advice is in the phrasing. &#8220;I am a disciplined person who goes to the gym&#8221; is a very different thought than &#8220;you will go to the gym you lazy sack of shit&#8221;. Both seem like motivation, but only one works.</p>

<p>Start listening to yourself. To the tone, the mood, and the phrasing. Separate yourself from your internal dialogue.</p>

<p>Only then can you start sticking to your goals.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
