<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Nate Speller]]></title>
  <link href="http://ogn8.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ogn8.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-20T00:41:58-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ogn8.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nathan Speller]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Way You Say It Matters]]></title>
    <link href="http://ogn8.com/blog/2012/10/27/phrasing/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-27T12:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ogn8.com/blog/2012/10/27/phrasing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are a ton of books written on <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Talk-Kids-Will-Listen/dp/1451663889/">how to talk to children</a>. One topic I see frequently is how to properly phrase criticism. The idea is that when a child misbehaves, it&#8217;s said that you should denounce the action, yet praise the child. i.e. &#8220;she is a good kid who has done something wrong&#8221; - rather than &#8220;she is a terrible kid.&#8221;</p>

<p>Interestingly, anyone can apply this advice to their internal dialogue to learn what they think of themselves. For example, many people will say to themselves, &#8220;I&#8217;ve always been a lazy guy, but today I got a lot of work done - I did good today.&#8221;</p>

<p>Sounds okay, but this person actually defines himself as an unmotivated person who has happened to do something good. Alternatively, you might say &#8220;I accomplished a lot today because I&#8217;m disciplined and dedicated to achieving my goal. I may have had some setbacks but not today.&#8221; Similar, but very different.</p>

<p>Now lets look at some advice you&#8217;ve surely heard before:</p>

<blockquote>&#8220;There are those who think they will succeed and those who think they will fail. In the end, both are right.&#8221;</blockquote>


<p>This seems obvious, but it&#8217;s surprisingly easy to mess this up. The subtlety to this advice is in the phrasing. &#8220;You are a disciplined person who goes to the gym&#8221; is a very different thought than &#8220;you will go to the gym you lazy bum.&#8221; Both seem like motivation, but one isn&#8217;t motivation at all.</p>

<p>Start listening to your internal dialogue. To the tone, the mood, and the phrasing. Separate yourself from your inner voice and you&#8217;ll learn a lot about what you think of yourself.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mood Killers]]></title>
    <link href="http://ogn8.com/blog/2012/10/20/tone/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-20T12:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ogn8.com/blog/2012/10/20/tone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here&#8217;s a self-awareness tip.</p>

<p>While thinking through your problems, your mood can easily cloud your judgement. However, sometimes you&#8217;ll get so lost in your internal dialogue that you won&#8217;t realize the additional stress you&#8217;re causing yourself.</p>

<blockquote>&#8220;Ugh, I&#8217;m so lazy. I gotta start exercising. Where did these rolls come from?? I can&#8217;t go out with a gut like this. Oh they&#8217;re looking at me now.&#8221;</blockquote>


<p>In these cases, the actual words of your internal dialogue don&#8217;t matter. What matters is the tone. Stop and take out the words, using only &#8220;mmm&#8221; sounds and you&#8217;ll quickly discover the mood you&#8217;re in. Sounding whiny? Kill that internal dialogue on spot, make a decision, and stop worrying.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Success is Silent]]></title>
    <link href="http://ogn8.com/blog/2012/10/14/internal-dialogue/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-14T22:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ogn8.com/blog/2012/10/14/internal-dialogue</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a given day, who do you talk to most? A co-worker? Best friend? A significant other?</p>

<p>I&#8217;m willing to bet that there&#8217;s another person you speak to more. One that never stops talking to you, and never waits for your response. One that criticizes all your actions, second-guesses all your decisions, and nags you endlessly about how little you&#8217;ve accomplished. No, it&#8217;s not your mother and it&#8217;s not your ex.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s you.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s that voice in your head that never seems to quit:</p>

<blockquote>&#8220;I&#8217;ll start that personal project tomorrow.&#8221;<br>
&#8220;Geez, everyone else is so much more successful.&#8221;</blockquote>


<blockquote>&#8220;Just one more article and then I&#8217;ll start my work.&#8221;<br>
&#8220;Ugh, I&#8217;m so lazy.&#8221;</blockquote>


<blockquote>&#8220;Just one more slice of pie.&#8221;<br>
  &#8220;OMG I&#8217;m so fat.&#8221;</blockquote>


<p>You&#8217;ve tried to fix the situation with <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=btPJPFnesV4">motivational</a> <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lsSC2vx7zFQ">youtube</a> <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lSM1mvMypWU">videos</a>, new workout tapes, the latest to-do lists (and to-do lists for your to-do lists). You get excited about your new found motivation. &#8220;I got this!!! There&#8217;s no way I can fail this time!!&#8221;</p>

<p>And yet, two weeks later you&#8217;re on the couch watching New Girl with your best friends Ben and Jerry.</p>

<p>Ironically, the problem is not your inability to stay &#8220;motivated.&#8221; Anyone can get excited about their goals for a short period of time (it&#8217;s called New Years). However, sustaining this amount of motivation is not only impractical but almost impossible. In order to really make progress you have to keep trucking when the motivation is gone.</p>

<p>But what&#8217;s left when the motivation is gone? Just that voice in your head; the internal dialogue that persuades you with &#8220;I&#8217;ll get started&#8230;tomorrow.&#8221;</p>

<p>Silence this voice and you&#8217;ll make real progress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
