<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Nathan Speller]]></title>
  <link href="http://nathanspeller.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nathanspeller.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-25T04:24:38-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://nathanspeller.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nathan Speller]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Few Paths to Success]]></title>
    <link href="http://nathanspeller.com/paths-to-success/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-19T15:50:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://nathanspeller.com/paths-to-success</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Step 1. Steal Underpants <br>
Step 2. ????? <br>
Step 3. PROFIT</p>

<p>Know this meme? It&#8217;s from a <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tO5sxLapAts">South Park episode</a> in 1998, fifteen years ago!! It is hilariously ridiculous and unfortunately the strategy many startups operate under today. Let me explain.</p>

<p>You&#8217;re a first time entreprenuer on Step 1. Your company is in the early stages, readying for a product launch, working with initial customers, making moves. In fact, it&#8217;s been that way for a while. You&#8217;ve had some small wins, and some setbacks, but you persist; you continue to steal underpants, for success is just around the corner, right?</p>

<p>Now take a moment to think about your goals. Where do you want your company to end up? I&#8217;m sure you could paint me a vivid picture of your Google-acquired startup, and your traveling lifestyle, filled with fame and fortune. Your Step 3 is as clear as day.</p>

<p>But what is your plan for Step 2? For this we need to take a closer look at the entrepreneurial landscape and the limited paths to success. Then we can better understand the game we&#8217;re playing and the strategies needed to succeed.</p>

<h3>Success is rare</h3>

<p>At any given point there are an infinite number of tasks your company can be working on: promoting, building, hiring, networking, etc. Lets assume that every set of decisions represents a path to either success or failure. Unfortunately, most of these paths lead to failure (see the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_law">power law</a>). The CS degree that I&#8217;m still paying for says I should visualize this as a search tree.</p>

<p><img src="http://ogblog.s3.amazonaws.com/paths-to-success-graph.png" /></p>

<p>If the problem is presented this way, there are a few conclusions we can make. First, succeeding on intuition alone is nearly impossible. You are inexperienced and there are just too many paths to consider. (In fact, this model doesn&#8217;t even take into account that luck is a very real factor and most of the paths are unknown i.e. you can&#8217;t see the paths you don&#8217;t think of).</p>

<p>Second, before you succeed you must fail many times. Learning what doesn&#8217;t work and backtracking is a necessary step. In fact, it&#8217;s the <strong>most common event you&#8217;ll face</strong>. Yet most founders will avoid it like the plague. They keep doing what they&#8217;re doing, hoping for change (instead of measuring it), and rationalizing their decisions along the way.</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;We&#8217;ll be successful as soon as we launch.&#8221;<br>&#8220;Our sales will blow up after we finish that feature.&#8221;<br>&#8220;If we get just a little more funding, it&#8217;ll work.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>We lose sight of our progress, or lack thereof, and get stuck in the proverbial weeds. The reality is that most startups rarely question the path they&#8217;re on. They will&#8230;</p>

<ul>
<li> build for years without ever speaking to potential customers</li>
<li> spend months making an unwanted product scalable</li>
<li> hold off product launches (read potential failure) until they&#8217;re <em>really</em> ready</li>
<li> plan inventory management systems for a product nobody wants</li>
<li> spam the internet with their new service and wonder why no one will buy it</li>
<li> blindly, prematurely push sales because the investors expect growth</li>
<li> waste time coming up with solutions to questions no one has asked</li>
</ul>


<p>This happens because we&#8217;re not using a systematic approach to solving our entrepreneurial problems. We let our intuition (read irrational emotions) guide our choices and rarely take the time to evaluate our decisions.</p>

<p>We need a strategy.</p>

<p>There is the Lean Startup method, customer-driven development, the scientific method and many more. We&#8217;ve heard their principles, although we don&#8217;t really follow them. For most of us they&#8217;ve been reduced to networking buzz words.</p>

<p>Although you may not use any of these methods, you must have some sort of method. The particular steps are not what&#8217;s important here. What&#8217;s important is the common thread these methods share: systematic feedback and reevaluation. That is, regularly stepping back and reevaluating your progress, hypotheses, and decisions (your path) based on new information you&#8217;ve learned.</p>

<p>Always be able to answer the following:</p>

<ul>
<li> What questions are you trying to answer?</li>
<li> When will you get that answer?</li>
<li> What metrics do you use to measure progress?</li>
<li> How often do you reevaluate?</li>
<li> What have you learned from past failures?</li>
<li> Why are you doing what you&#8217;re doing?</li>
<li> What are you trying to learn?</li>
<li> Is there a faster cheaper way to get the information you need?</li>
</ul>


<p>This is the only way to systematically remove &#8220;failure paths&#8221; without wasting valuable time and energy.</p>

<p>Startups deal with so much uncertainty that you can&#8217;t just work harder or longer hours. It doesn&#8217;t matter if you launch your product in six weeks instead of seven. Because without a method, six weeks can quickly become six months in the wrong direction.</p>

<p>Instead, you must work smarter. You must run your company like a laboratory. Ask the right questions. Create hypotheses. Create experiments to test your assumptions. Measure, measure, measure. Accept that most of your experiments will fail. Keep track of everything you learn. And repeat.</p>

<p>Success awaits at the top of a mountain built of failures and lessons learned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taking Responsibility]]></title>
    <link href="http://nathanspeller.com/taking-responsibility/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-13T23:39:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://nathanspeller.com/taking-responsibility</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>More often than not, bad stuff happens in the startup world. Customers complain, deals fall through, cofounders leave. When things get tough it&#8217;s easy to blame the external circumstances. &#8220;That investor screwed us over!&#8221; &#8220;That cofounder left us with nothing!&#8221;</p>

<p>Then I watch a superhero movie. You watch these guys (Batman, Spiderman, Ryan Gosling), who feel it is their duty to save the world. At any point they can give up and say &#8220;not my responsibility&#8221; but they persist.</p>

<p>They make my problems look so small. They make my problems look like… opportunities.</p>

<p>And I realize, I just need to take responsibility. Responsibility for my actions, for my team, and for my results. When I do, there&#8217;s no one to blame.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Way You Say It Matters]]></title>
    <link href="http://nathanspeller.com/phrasing/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-27T12:44:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://nathanspeller.com/phrasing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are a ton of books written on <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Talk-Kids-Will-Listen/dp/1451663889/">how to talk to children</a>. One topic I see frequently is how to properly phrase criticism. The idea is that when a child misbehaves, it&#8217;s said that you should denounce the action, yet praise the child. i.e. &#8220;she is a good kid who has done something wrong&#8221; - rather than &#8220;she is a terrible kid.&#8221;</p>

<p>Interestingly, anyone can apply this advice to their internal dialogue to learn what they think of themselves. For example, many people will say to themselves, &#8220;I&#8217;ve always been a lazy guy, but today I got a lot of work done - I did good today.&#8221;</p>

<p>Sounds okay, but this person actually defines himself as an unmotivated person who has happened to do something good. Alternatively, you might say &#8220;I accomplished a lot today because I&#8217;m disciplined and dedicated to achieving my goal. I may have had some setbacks but not today.&#8221; Similar, but very different.</p>

<p>Now lets look at some advice you&#8217;ve surely heard before:</p>

<blockquote>&#8220;There are those who think they will succeed and those who think they will fail. In the end, both are right.&#8221;</blockquote>


<p>This seems obvious, but it&#8217;s surprisingly easy to mess this up. The subtlety to this advice is in the phrasing. &#8220;You are a disciplined person who goes to the gym&#8221; is a very different thought than &#8220;you will go to the gym you lazy bum.&#8221; Both seem like motivation, but one isn&#8217;t motivation at all.</p>

<p>Start listening to your internal dialogue. To the tone, the mood, and the phrasing. Separate yourself from your inner voice and you&#8217;ll learn a lot about what you think of yourself.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mood Killers]]></title>
    <link href="http://nathanspeller.com/tone/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-20T12:43:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://nathanspeller.com/tone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here&#8217;s a self-awareness tip.</p>

<p>While thinking through your problems, your mood can easily cloud your judgement. However, sometimes you&#8217;ll get so lost in your internal dialogue that you won&#8217;t realize the additional stress you&#8217;re causing yourself.</p>

<blockquote>&#8220;Ugh, I&#8217;m so lazy. I gotta start exercising. Where did these rolls come from?? I can&#8217;t go out with a gut like this. Oh they&#8217;re looking at me now.&#8221;</blockquote>


<p>In these cases, the actual words of your internal dialogue don&#8217;t matter. What matters is the tone. Stop and take out the words, using only &#8220;mmm&#8221; sounds and you&#8217;ll quickly discover the mood you&#8217;re in. Sounding whiny? Kill that internal dialogue on spot, make a decision, and stop worrying.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Success is Silent]]></title>
    <link href="http://nathanspeller.com/internal-dialogue/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-14T22:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://nathanspeller.com/internal-dialogue</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a given day, who do you talk to most? A co-worker? Best friend? A significant other?</p>

<p>I&#8217;m willing to bet that there&#8217;s another person you speak to more. One that never stops talking to you, and never waits for your response. One that criticizes all your actions, second-guesses all your decisions, and nags you endlessly about how little you&#8217;ve accomplished. No, it&#8217;s not your mother and it&#8217;s not your ex.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s you.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s that voice in your head that never seems to quit:</p>

<blockquote>&#8220;I&#8217;ll start that personal project tomorrow.&#8221;<br>
&#8220;Geez, everyone else is so much more successful.&#8221;</blockquote>


<blockquote>&#8220;Just one more article and then I&#8217;ll start my work.&#8221;<br>
&#8220;Ugh, I&#8217;m so lazy.&#8221;</blockquote>


<blockquote>&#8220;Just one more slice of pie.&#8221;<br>
  &#8220;OMG I&#8217;m so fat.&#8221;</blockquote>


<p>You&#8217;ve tried to fix the situation with <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=btPJPFnesV4">motivational</a> <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lsSC2vx7zFQ">youtube</a> <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lSM1mvMypWU">videos</a>, new workout tapes, the latest to-do lists (and to-do lists for your to-do lists). You get excited about your new found motivation. &#8220;I got this!!! There&#8217;s no way I can fail this time!!&#8221;</p>

<p>And yet, two weeks later you&#8217;re on the couch watching New Girl with your best friends Ben and Jerry.</p>

<p>Ironically, the problem is not your inability to stay &#8220;motivated.&#8221; Anyone can get excited about their goals for a short period of time (it&#8217;s called New Years). However, sustaining this amount of motivation is not only impractical but almost impossible. In order to really make progress you have to keep trucking when the motivation is gone.</p>

<p>But what&#8217;s left when the motivation is gone? Just that voice in your head; the internal dialogue that persuades you with &#8220;I&#8217;ll get started&#8230;tomorrow.&#8221;</p>

<p>Silence this voice and you&#8217;ll make real progress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
